NIRANJAN GANESAN

PHONE: 07308161523 Email: niranjan27494@gmail.com





Software Engineer with 3.5 years of experience in development, operations, testing and support to consumer applications. Supportive and enthusiastic team player passionate for finding technical solutions to customer problems using available resources and looking for challenging role to enhance the current skillset.

EXPERIENCE

IBM - SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (CONTR.)

FEB 2018 - AUG 2019

- Mainframe Application Programmer on UPS's Logistics web application, Requirements analysis, gathering research data, design, coding testing and release.
- Production Support, Batch monitoring, Change request implementation.
- Unit Testing, System integration testing, Regression testing and Acceptance testing on CICS web services.
- Software Development using Agile practices.
- Generate automation test scripts using Vugen and create performance test results using HP performance center.
- Handle huge volumes of customer data on relational database management systems.
- Guiding and teaching junior colleagues on new projects.

CAPGEMINI – SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

OCT 2015 - SEP 2017

- Mainframe Application Programmer on Synchrony's Credit Application Software Development, Requirement analysis, gathering research data, design, coding, testing and release.
- Batch monitoring, Production support, Automation and system maintenance.
- Ad-hoc report generation and preparation of daily, weekly and monthly reports.
- Software upgrade support on Mainframe servers.
- Software development using waterfall method.
- Technical support to software upgrades on mainframe servers.
- Automation of daily tasks that reduces manual effort.

EDUCATION

MSc BIG DATA SCIENCE - QUEEN MARY UNIVERSITY OF LONDON

2019 - 2020

Relevant Modules – Data Mining, Applied Statistics, Big Data Processing, Machine Learning, Cloud Computing, Deep Learning and Computer Vision, Data Analytics, Machine Learning for Visual Data Analysis.

BEng ELECTRONICS AND COMMUNICATION ENGINEERING (1st Equivalent) - ANNA UNIVERSITY, INDIA 2011 – 2015

Relevant Modules - Computer Networks, Digital Signal Processing, Wireless Networks, Digital Electronics, Wireless communications, Signals and Systems. **CGPA – 7.27/10**

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Experience Supporting Banking and Logistics Industry
- Software Development using Agile practices and waterfall method.
- Daily batch cycle monitoring. Providing 24/7 support for batch job abends and application issues.
- Skilled communicator, able to influence across boundaries
- Providing hands-on analysis, programming, configuration, testing and implementation support to assigned systems and/or projects
- Immediate response to critical issues, fixing critical software issues with minimal or no business impact as soon as possible.
- Providing technical guidance and mentorship to less experienced employees.

- Data Analysis
- Data Visualization
- Machine Learning
- Python
- Java Script
- Pandas
- Hadoop
- SQL
- Spark
- Cloud Computing
- AWS
- Rest API
- Jupyter
- Data Science

PROJECTS AND CERTIFICATIONS

Applied Data Science Capstone – New Cineplex in London, United Kingdom

The objective of this project is to analyze and select the best locations in the city of London to open a new Cineplex. Using data science methodology and machine learning techniques like clustering, this project aims to provide solutions to answer the business question: In a multi-cultural city like London, if a property developer is looking to open a new Cineplex, where would you recommend, they open it?

Github Link - https://github.com/niranjanganesan/Coursera Capstone

Big Data Analysis on Ethereum Blockchain

The objective of this project is to analyze the big datasets of Ethereum Blockchain data and derive insights from it using Big Data tools such as Hadoop and Spark. Time Analysis – number of transactions every month, Top 10 most popular services, Exploratory Data Analysis on gas, scams and more.

Github Link - https://github.com/niranjanganesan/Big-Data

• IBM Certified Data Science Professional

OTHER ROLES OF RESPONSIBILITY

- Music, Theatre and Dance Trained Professional dancer with numerous stage performances over the period of 8 years.
- Media and Technical skills Audio and video editor for college promotional and cultural videos. Photo editor for College Newsletter.
- Leadership Class representative for two consecutive years at my undergraduate university.
- Entrepreneurship Sales and Marketing apprentice for an event management startup.
- Sports Member of football committee at my undergraduate university.
- Volunteering Member of Backstage organizing crew for various dance and arts performances.

REFERENCES AVAILABLE ON REQUEST